大家好
hey, every guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么，上次，我们设置了
so，last time，we set up
一个创建OpenGL窗口和上下文的GLFW库
an OpenGL windowing and context library called GLFW
基本上
which basically
只是让我们认为有创建跨平台窗口的能力
just gave us the ability to credit cross-platform window
以及为OpenGL初始化一个图形上下文
and initialized a graphics context for OpenGL where
就是我们所有绘制的地方
we could do all about drawing
如果你还没看那集视频
if you haven't seen that video yet
你可一定要去看看
make sure you check it out
因为那对这集视频还是挺重要
because it's gonna be important for this video here
在屏幕上，我们已经得到了一个三角形
and we even got a triangle onto the screen
并且一切看起来都没什么问题
and everything looked like it was working properly
的确如此
and well it was
然而，你可能已经注意到了，上集
however what you might have noticed in the previous video is that
实际上，我们链接了opengl32.lib
we actually linked something called opengl32.lib
并且我们最终用的头文件
and the header of files that we actually ended up using for
特别是隐藏OpenGL函数的头文件
sophistic specifically for OpenGL functions
基本上，我们使用的GLFW提供了
we're basically the ones that either GLFW provided which
依次调整Windows图形
in turn adjust the Windows ones
不过现在，Windows已经有了一个图形接口
now,Windows has a graphics api already
它叫DirectX
it's called DirectX or Direct3D
或者是更具体一点的Direct3D
or Direct3D to be a little bit more specific
这就是Windows所使用的
that's what Windows uses
这就是你该使用的
that's what you should kind of be using
根据微软的说法
according to Microsoft
这就是你在Windows上绘图应该使用的图形接口
that's what you should be using to do graphics on Windows
并且这是有一定道理的
and it makes sense
并且就我个人而言，对于一个
and me personally for a
对于开发一个真实的游戏
for a real kind of game
对于开发一个游戏引擎的实际项目
for a real project for a game engine
在Windows上，我可能会用Direct3D来渲染
I would be using Direct3D to render on Windows
因为这是平台原生的图形接口
because that's what's native to the platform
这也是你应该用的图形接口
that's what you kind of should be using
至于OpenGL，请记住
OpenGL, though, remember
不是由Windows决定的
is not kind of up to Windows to decide
如果有的话
if that's a thing or not
它取决于我们显卡的制造商
it's up to our GPU manufacturers
取决于显卡的驱动
it's up to the GPU drivers
并且，来自NVIDIA和AMD以及Intel的显卡驱动
and, and, and the GPU drivers from NVIDIA and AMD and Intel
它们都支持OpenGL作为渲染接口
they all support OpenGL as a rendering api
所以，我们现在需要做的
so, what we need to do now
并不是真的那么依赖Windows
is not really rely on windows
它们只是OpenGL的头文件
and they're kind of OpenGL header files which
只到OpenGL 1.1的版本
only go up to OpenGL 1.1
那是OpenGL的最后一个版本
which is kind of the last version of OpenGL
那也是第一个版本
which is also kind of the first version
1.0有点奇怪
1.0 was kind of a bit weird
我们一般不讨论它
we don't talk about that
1.1，OpenGL 1.1是最后一个
1.1, OpenGL 1.1 was kind of the last
也是OpenGL第一个实际的版本
the...the first real version of OpenGL
但是
and that
关于这个，我们就说到这里吧
that's as far as we discuss with it
所以，当我们在Windows上
so, since we're on windows
实际上，我需要一种方法去得到
we need a way to actually get
所有现代OpenGL的函数
all of the modern OpenGL functions
不不不，我甚至不是在说现代OpenGL
not even, I'm not even talking about modern ones
我只是在说
I'm just talking about
1997年以后的新东西，懂了吧
anything newer than like 1997, right
一个接一个的OpenGL函数
OpenGL one by one
在那(1997)之后的一切
anything anything newer than that
实际上，如果我们需要调用这些函数
if we want to actually call those functions
现在你们说的是c++代码
you now say c++ code
我们需要从一些地方得到那些函数
we need to get them from somewhere
并且，我注意到在“欢迎来到OpenGL”的视频
and as I mentioned in the welcome to OpenGL video
就是第一个链接那里的视频
which was the first one get linking up there
OpenGL函数…
OpenGL functions
它不是你真正下载的一些东西
it's not something you download really
实际上，它是你显卡驱动中一种东西
it's stuff that is actually in your graphics drivers
OpenGL函数是在你的显卡驱动中被实现的
the OpenGL functions are implemented in your GPU drivers
那么，我们现在需要做的就是
so, what we need to do now is
为了去使用这些功能
in order to use any kind of functionality
在OpenGL 1.1版本中比较新的那些
that is newer, that OpenGL 1.1
实际上，我们需要去访问这些驱动
we need to actually get into those drivers
取出函数，并且调用它们
pull out the functions and call them
那我说取出这些函数到底是什么呢
now what I say pull out the functions
并不是我字面上说的把函数取出来
I don't literally mean pull out the functions
我们实际上需要做的
what we actually need to do
基本上就是得到函数声明
is basically just get the function declarations
然后把链接到对应的函数上
and then link against the functions as well
所以，我们需要访问驱动的动态链接库文件
so we need to access the driver dll files
然后只检索库里面那些函数的函数指针
and just retrieve function pointers to the functions inside those libraries
这就是我们需要做的
that's what we need to do
现在，OpenGL
now, OpenGL
经过了1.1版本，基本上都是现代OpenGL了
passed 1.1, so basically modern OpenGL and all of that
有许多函数
there are a lot of functions
确实有许多函数
所以理论上来说，我们可以动手做这个
so whilst we could theoretically do this manually
但它有一点儿问题
there are a few problems with that
首先
first of all
它不可能是跨平台的
it would not be cross-platform
所以，总的来说
so, to basically
访问显卡驱动并从中取出这些函数
access the drivers and pull out functions from that
我们需要使用一些Win32接口调用
we need to use some Win32 api calls
当我们在Windows上的时候，对吧
if we're on Windows right
载入库，然后载入函数指针等等
load library and load function pointers to all that
但这并不太好
that's not great
因为它只能在Windows上用
because it's gonna be Windows only
其次，第二个问题是
and then the second problem is
如果是…
if there are like
我也不知道
I don't know
超过1K个函数或之类的一些事情
over 1000 functions or something like that
那么我们需要手动完成所有这些操作
then we need to go through all of the manually
并且为它们写代码
and write code for that
那将是一个糟糕的计划
that's gonna just be a terrible plan
这一点都不好玩
it's just not gonna be fun at all
所以，我们现在做的就是
so what we're gonna do now is
我们实际上需要使用另一个库
we're actually gonna use another library
现在这儿有一些库
now there are a few libraries
确实能帮你做这些
that actually do this for you
但是，我只想让你们这些家伙明白
but, i just want you guys to  understand
这个库(GLEW)到底是如何运行的
that what this library actually does
其实很简单的
is actually really straightforward
你自己可以去看看这个库的源码
and you can look at the source code for this library for yourself
如果你需要就去看看它是如何运行的，如果你喜欢的话
and see what it does if you want, if you like
但基本上，它能做的就是为你提供
but basically all it does is it provides
OpenGL接口规范
the OpenGL api specification
各种函数声明，符号声明和常量
kind of function declarations and symbol declarations and constants
诸如此类的东西
and all that stuff
在一个头文件各种
for you in a header of file
然后这种背后的文件
and then the kind of the behind-the-scenes file
这种场景的C++文件，我认为它是安全的文件
the cpp file on this scenes, I think it' about safe file
这个库的实际实现
the actual implementation of the library
就是进入EDI，在你使用的显卡驱动签名中
goes into your EDI, it identifies what graphics drivers you're using
查找对应的动态链接文件
finds the appropriate dll file
然后载入所有这些函数指针
and then loads all of the function pointers
这就是它所能做的
that's what it does that's all it does
它非常非常无聊，一点儿也不神奇
it's very very boring, it's not magical at all
不要认为这些库实现了一些函数或其他东西
don't think that these libraries implement the functions or anything
它们并没有
they don't
它们只是访问这些函数
they just access the functions
那些函数早就以二进制的形式存在你电脑上了
that are already on your computer in binary form
并且我们使用的这个库只是为我们做了
and the library that we're going to use that does that for us
一些事情，比如GLUE，不对，应该是GREW，OpenGL扩展管理
is something called GLUE or GLEW, the OpenGL extension wrangler
这儿也有一个GLAD库
there's also another library called GLAD
如果你喜欢，你也可以用它
you can use that if you like
这是OpenGL的一个比较特殊的扩展
it's a bit more specific with extensions to OpenGL and all that stuff
并且你也可以更好的配置它
and you can configure it a little bit better
但我真的不是很在意这些
I don't really care about that
我们只是尝试去写OpenGL的代码
we're just trying to write OpenGL code and
GLEW就能做到我需要的一切
GLEW does everything I need
而且它也比较简单
it is a little bit simpler
所以我们就用GLEW
so we're going to use GLEW
所以，我们第一件要做的事就是，访问glew.sourceforget.net
so the first thing we're going to do is go to glew.sourceforget.net
再说一下，这个链接我会放在描述里
again link will be in the description
这就是GLEW的网站
this is the GLEW website
如果需要的话，我们也有机会下载源码
again we have the opportunity to download the source code if we want it
并且这事儿我绝对会干的
and that is what I would absolutely be doing
如果这是一个严格的项目或一个游戏引擎
if this was a serious project or a game engin
然而，这只是关于学习OpenGL的
however because this is just about learning OpenGL
并且这只是让我们能够写OpenGL代码的东西
and this is something that enables us to write OpenGL code
一点儿也不在意这些细节
I don't care about that
我只需要下载对应Windows的二进制文件
I'm just going to get the binaries for Windows
在这儿，点击这个链接
I'm going to click on this link here
然后直到它下载完成
and then once it's downloaded
打开这个压缩包
I'm going to open the zip archive
这儿有个文件夹glew-2.1.0
and there'll be a folder there called glue 2.1
在这种情况下，我就复制这个文件夹
in this case, I'm just going to copy that
回到OpenGL方案的实际目录
I'm going to go back into our actual directory of our OpenGL solution
就像上次我们复制GLFW到Dependences文件夹一样
and just like last time where we put GLFW inside the Dependencies folder
也把GLEW粘贴到Dependencies文件夹来，好了
I'm going to paste GLEW into this Dependency folder as well, okay
那么我们进去看看
so here we go and inside that GLEW folder
现在，我们已经有了想要的一切东西
we have everything we need now
实际上，我还要把它重命名为GLEW，好了
one thing I'm actually going to do is rename this to just GLEW, okay
之前这种明显带版本的，真没太必要
not really necessary and does kind of strip the version it's obviously before
很明显，这就是glew-2.1.0
it was obvious to tell that this was glew-2.1.0
现在，你真的不需要知道GLEW到底是什么版本的
now you don't really know what version of GLEW is
我刚刚只是做了一点简化
I'm just doing this for simplification
目的就是对我们来说更容易一点
kind of purposes just so that it's a bit easier for us
现在，我们已经有了GLEW和GLFW
but now we have GLEW and GLFW as well
在GLEW目录中，我们有一些不同的文件夹
so inside this, we have a few different folders
include和lib是为了链接的，我们需要注意的是
the ones that we kind of care about for linking, as well as include and lib
这和链接GLFW完全一样
this is exactly the same as linking GLFW
这是我们上集做的
so that was an episode to check that out
如果你还没看过
if you haven't already
我也制作了一个视频
I also just made a video
关于，如何在c++中链接库
about how linking libraries in c++ actually works
以及，如何在c++中使用库
and how you can use libraries in c++
那儿有链接
that's linked up there
一定要去看看
check that out for sure
那可以帮助你理解这儿在做什么
that'll help you understand what's going on here
因为这次我尽量保持简短点儿
because I'm going to try and keep this brief this time
所以doc文件夹也包含了你需要的各种各样的文档
so doc, also includes all the kind of documentation that you want
你看看
you can see
这只是一种html形式的，所以，你可以直接打开index.html
it's just an html format, so you can just open up index.html
那是主页面
that's the main web page
让我们在谷歌浏览器中打开吧
let's open it in Chrome
并且我看到了和那个网站页面一样的东西
and we have something that looks exactly the same as the web page
但是你现在看到的这个页面是本地的
but you can see that this one is local
所以这就是比较重要的阅读文档的地方
so this is where reading documentation is kind of important
如果我们访问Usage页面
if we go to Usage
首先，它告诉我们
first of all, it tells us
如何去初始化它
how to actually initialize this issues
现在，我要指出一些问题，就是
now I'm going to point out a few
你可能会遇到GLEW
you might encounter with GLEW
如果你没有阅读文档
if you don't read the documentation
我现在能想到两点，可能不太明显
there's two that I can think of right now, that might not be apparent
第一点，实际上也就是字面上的第一个东西
the first one is actually literally the first thing
文档这里提到
that this documentation says
首先，你需要创建一个有效的渲染OpenGL上下文
and that is first you need to create a valid OpenGL rendering context
然后调用glewInit()去初始化扩展的入口
and call glewInit() to initialize the extension entry points
所以你不能直接从GLEW中直接调用OpenGL函数
so you can't use OpenGL functions from GLEW
直到你调用了glewInit()
until you call glewInit()
这是第一点。然后，它提到的第二点是
that's the first one and second of all as it says
你需要创建一个渲染OpenGL的上下文
you need to create a valid OpenGL rendering context
在你调用glewInit()之前
before you call glewInit()
那么，在我们源码中，已经有了glfwInit()
so over here in our source code, we have glfwInit()
如果我们在这儿调用glewInit()
if we want to call glewInit() here
它会正常运行吗，会发生什么
would it work and what
我现在也不知道，等等看吧
I'm not going to answer that right now, we'll see
总之，先回到文档
anyway, back to the documentation
它明确地告诉我们，如何去初始化，我们调用了glewInit()
it tells us exactly how to kind of initialize this, glewInit() that we call
然后我们去检查它的返回值
and then we can check to see if that return code from glewInit()
如果它返回的GLenum整数
if that return integer of GLenum
它只是一个整数
which is just an intege
可能是GLEW_OK，或者不是
is GLEW_OK or not
如果返回值不是GLEW_OK的话，我们可能有点儿问题
and if it's not GLEW_OK that means we have a problem
所以，看起来很容易
so pretty easy to tell here
这里也有很多关于扩展的诸如此类的东西，
there's a bunch of stuff about extensions here as well and all that stuff
现在，在这个的构建部分
now in the building section of this
也有大量对构建它比较重要的一些东西
we have a bunch of things that are important for building this
但是，我们不需要关注这些
but again we don't really care about that
同样，在安装这部分
and also in the installation section
你可以看到，这儿也列了一些东西
you can see that there are some things listed
关于如何构建库
about how to build library as well
如果你们尝试把它作为共享库，诸如此类的一切
if you're trying to use it as a shared library, and all that stuff anything
我们可能会自己去探索发现
we'll kind of explore it and find out for ourselves as well
但只是另一个提醒
but just but just another reminder
如果你只是在使用一个新库的时候
if you're using a new library
阅读这个文档
read the documentation
那样做并没什么好处
it doesn't hurt to do that
它可能会浪费一点点时间
it might take a little bit of time
但总之
but overall
你可能明白这些事，刚开始需要
you might see things that first of all are going to
防止你意外犯错
prevent you from accidentally doing things incorrectly
然后扣你的头发，因为它没有正常工作
and then pulling your hair up because it's not working
这就是那样做可能可能出现的情况
whereas it appears that it might it should be
当然
and also
你也可能这么说
you might be able to say that
嗷，实际上，我会用我想到的方式去做它
oh, I can actually use it in a way that i'm think of
虽然，真的很重要的就是
the really important thing though is that
这是c++
this is c++
我们在c++中运行代码
we're running code in c++
并且c++允许你做事情
and c++ allows you to do things
通过很多很多
in many many
很多方式，很多不同的方式
many ways many different ways
并且特别是，当你刚接触c++时
and especially if you're new to c++
你可能这样想，好吧
you might think okay
我使用的每个库
every library I use
遵循这种过程，遵循这种风格
follows this progression, follows this kind of style
但你不能这样假设
you can't assume that
在c++中，做这个东西有许多方法
there's so many ways to do stuff in c++
并且，每个人都认为他们的做法都是对的
and everyone thinks that they're doing it the right way
所以
so
当你需要去阅读这个文档时
when you need to do is read the documentation and
请不要做任何假设
don't make assumptions
因为那可能会让一些事情变得很扯蛋
because they might be doing something crazy
他们可能会为某些事情定义他们自己元语言，诸如此类的
they might be defining their own meta language for certain things, or whatever,
你不能假设那些东西
you can't kind of assume that stuff
所以，阅读文档是比较重要的
so, documentation is important to read
无论如何，我之前已经阅读过了
anyway, I've done this before
所以，现在，我不准备全部再次看一遍
so I'm not going to read all of this right now
让我们在项目中配置这个吧
but let's set this up with our project
我已经把所有都解压在这儿了
so I've extracted all of this here
再说一次，我们已经看过文档了
again we've looked at the documentation
bin这个文件夹里面包含了release
bin, contains inside release
我们有x64和Win32，这里有我们的dll文件
we have x64 and Win32, which has our dll file
不过我真的不太关心这些
I don't really care about that
因为我们会用静态链接
because we're going to link this statically
请记住，你要尽可能的使用静态链接
remember you pretty much always want to link statically if you can
所以在include文件夹下，有我们实际需要包含的文件
so here inside include, we have our actual includes
你现在可能已经意识到了
you're probably realizing right now
那正是我们需要的路径
that this is exactly the path that we need to
添加到我们实际项目中的编译器include部分
add to our actual project to our compiler include parts
你是对的
and you are correct
那么，复制Dependences后面的部分
so I'm going to copy the end of that project after Dependencies
来到项目，右键OpenGL，点击属性
go to our project, right click on OpenGL, hit properties
然后就来到这儿
and then I'm going to go over here
选择配置，你可以看到这里是Debug
into configuration, you can see such a Debug
我只是想要保证那里是All Configurations
I'm just gonna make sure that that's on All Configurations
平台，Win32，很好
platform, Win32, is fine
在 c/c++ => 常规下面
inside c/c++ general
在这后面加个分号
I'm going to add a semicolon to the end of this
然后把我刚才复制的路径粘贴进去
and paste in this path i've copied
然后在这前面粘贴$(SolutionDir)
and then just stick solution directory to the front of that
现在你这儿可能有很多东西
now if there's a lot of stuff here
你不太想添加分号
and you don't really want to add semicolon
或者滚动这里
or scroll through this
你可以点击下拉按钮，然后点击编辑
you can just drop down this box here and here edit
你就可以看到
you can see that
在这儿，我们已经有了一个它们的列表
we have a list of them here
这样的话，他们就更容易被找到
and they're much easier to see
好了，完美
okay, fantastic
现在，我们就来说说链接库吧
let's talk about linking library now
所以当我们回到我们这里的文件夹时
so if we go back to our folder here
只需要回退一点点，然后进入
just going to go back a bit into
Dependencies, GLEW, 然后 lib
Dependencies, GLEW, and then lib
现在，就在release文件夹下了
now inside release
我们需要关注的就是Win32
and Win32 which is the one we care about
但这儿我们有两个lib文件
we've got two
你认为其中一个就是静态库
which one of these do you think is a static library
而另一个就是动态库
and which one do you think is the dynamic library
好吧，有些意外
well, plot-twists
从技术上来说，它们都是静态库
they're both technically static libraries
但是如果需要链接dll，你就要用这个glew32.lib
but this one is used if you want to link with the dll
这个glew32s.lib是在链接静态库时需要用到的
this one is used if you want to link with just the static library
因为这就是整个静态库
because this is the entire static library
所以，实际上，这两个之间的区别就是
so, the two things that give it away is the fact that
glew32s.lib这儿多了个一个s
this has an s, here
并且
and
还有就是，glew32s.lib明显比另一个要大一些
also that the size is significantly larger than the other one
记住，如果你这儿有个s，那可能代表静态库
remember if you have an s that probably stands for static again
这些都是你从经验中学到的
things that you kind of just learned with experience
所以glew32s.lib就是我们需要链接的库
so this is the one that we want to link again
复制这个目录路径
so I'm going to copy this directory path
进入链接器，常规
go into link and general
然后找到附加依赖库
and then additional library directories
展开下拉选项，然后点击编辑
I'm just gonna drop this down, here
可以让你们看起来更轻松一些
to make it easier for you guys to see
点击新增这个按钮
hit this new kind of thing button
然后只需要在这儿粘贴, 输入 $(SolutionDir)
and then just paste in, a solution directory over here
所以这就是我的路径
and my path
好了，看起来还不错
so there we go, looks pretty good to me
然后，我们连接的是GLEW
and then the one we're linking with remember is GLEW
这里的顺序无关紧要
doesn't really matter about the order here
在这里，我还需要glew32s.lib
in this case, either glew32s.lib is what I want
行了，非常棒，搞完了
okay, fantastic, done
现在，我应该可以调用glewInit()
now, I should be able to call glewInit()
然后让我们直接去包含头文件
and also let's just go ahead and
#include
include my path GL/glew.h
实际上，你可以看这儿
now if you actually look into here
这就是我知道这是GL而不是GLEW
the reason I know is GL and not GLEW
不管怎样，GLEW有GLEW，但glew没有
whatever, GLEW has GLEW but glew doesn't
理所应当
because of course
实际上，如果我看一下include目录里面
if I look in the actual include directory
这儿有一个GL文件夹，然后才是glew.h
there's a folder called GL and then glew.h
所以请记住这个路径
so remember the path the west specifying here
就是编译器包含的目录
is the path from this compiler include directory
我们已经包含的，好了，漂亮
that we've just included, okay,  great
所以，回到这儿，你可以看到
so back over here you can see that
这个运行成功
this works successfully
让我们尝试构建它
let's try building this
那么，点击这儿，然后点击构建，好了
so I'll right click here, and hit build, okay
所以马上就可以了
so it's right away
但实际上，我们看到了一个错误
we actually get an error
gl.h需要在glew.h之前包含
and it says gl.h included before glew.h
这是来自于
this is coming from
如果我们看这个输出窗口，这是来自于
if we look at the output, this is coming from
我们当前的glew.h头文件
our actual glew.h header file
所以，如果需要的话，我们可以双击这里
so we can double click here if we want
看看这里，所以原因
and we can take a look at this so the reason
出现这种是
this is happening is
由于这儿定义了一个字面上的哈希错误
because there's literally a hash error defined
这是一种编译时错误
which is a compile-time error
如果这些符号被定义的话，就会出现那种错误
that happens if these symbols are defined
所以基本上要你做的就是
so basically all this is asking you to do is
在包含任何其他OpenGL相关的头文件之前就要包含glew.h
please include this before you include any other OpenGL things
所以glfw的包含需要放到包含gl.h后面
so glfw appends to include gl.h
我们需要做的就是移动这个glew
so what we're going to do is just move this glew
在这之前，就这样
so that it's before this and that's it
再构建一次试试
let's try building this again
好了，太棒了
okay，awesome
我们编译成功了，然而，有一个链接错误
we compiled successfully, however we get a link error
现在, 链接错误是因为
now, link error is because
我们glewInit()符号导致的结果
on results our symbol glewInit()
现在，我们已经链接了一切，真是如此吗？
now we did link everything, didn't we?
那么，问题是什么
so what's the issue
那么，让我们看看，实际上，我们是如何设置GLEW的
well, let's take a look at how GLEW is actually set up
实际上，如果我们去GLEW的头文件，找这个glewInit函数
if we actually go to the GLEW header file, and we look for this glewInit function
你可以看到，这个宏定义GLEWAPI
you can see that we have this GLEWAPI kind of macro defined
在当前返回类型之前
before the actual return type
让我们看看那意味什么
let's take a look at what that means
当我跳转到这里
and if I jump over here
我们看这
we see this
有一个向我们解释它的注释
as well as a comment which kind of explains it for us
那么，GLEW_STATIC是为静态库定义的
so GLEW_STATIC is defined for static library
GLEW_BUILD是为动态库定义的
and GLEW_BUILD is defined for building the dll library
现在我们没有定义GLEW_STATIC
right now we don't have GLEW_STATIC defined
所以，这儿就是接下来发生的
so what's happening is it's coming over here
当然，GLEW_BUILD也没有定义
GLEW_BUILD isn't defined
所以，就运行到这儿了
so it's coming over here
实际上，它就定义了作为从dll文件导入的外部变量GLEWAPI
and it's actually defining GLEWAPI as extern _declspec(dllimport)
这是MSVC编译器固有的
which is an msvc compiler intrinsic
基本上就是告诉链接器
which basically tells the linker
这是来自于一个dll文件
this is coming from a dll file
你需要从dll文件中导入
you need to dll import this
到现在，我们并没有使用GLEW的动态库版本
now we're not using the dll version of GLEW
我们使用的是静态库
are we using the static library
所以如果我们像这样写代码的话
so if we write code like this
它是不可能链接到的
it's not gonna be able to link it
它只是不会运行
its...it's just not going to work
我们现在需要做的就是
we need to actually just
就像其他函数一样使用它
use it like any other function
当然，如果你找到这里
and of course if you look up here
你可以看到，如果GLEW_STATIC定义了的话
you can see that if GLEW_STATIC is defined
我们就不会通过dll导入导出来得到它
we don't get that kind of decalspec dll import or export export
当然如果你现在在编译的话，可能就需要从dll中导入导出了
of course is if you're actually building it
当我们需要从一个dll文件中导入的时候，它就比较重要了
import is for when we want to import it from a dll
所以我们需要
so we want to use this
我们实现它的方式就是定义GLEW_STATIC
and the way we do that is we define the GLEW_STATIC
这也是你可以得到的方法
again something that you could definitely get
如果你看了文档的话
if you read the documentation
但你没看的话
but if you don't
你可能需要对它进行逆向工程
you might have to kind of reverse engineer it
并且明确地知道它是如何运行的，然后指出
and actually look at how it works to figure out
如何让它编译和链接
how to get the stuff to compile and link
我只是想给你们展示一下
I just wanted to show you that to find basically
所以，当回到这里时，我们需要定义GLEW_STATIC
so if we go back to here, we need to define GLEW_STATIC
那么我要做的就是，右键点击我的项目
and I'm going to do that by right click on my project
来到项目属性这里
going to properties
找到c/c++
going to c/c++
预处理器
pre-processor
然后，这儿就是预处理器定义了
and then over here in are processor definitions
输入GLEW_STATIC
I'm going to type in GLEW_STATIC
然后回车
and hit enter again
不过确保我在所有配置，和Win32平台这里
making sure that I'm on All Configurations and Win32
点击确定，然后现在，构建我的项目
I hit okay and now I'm going to build my application
好了，非常棒
okay, awesome
那么，我们在输出窗口这里没看到任何错误，并且，我们的项目运行正常
so we don't get any errors here in our output and our applications fine
所以实际上，如果我们看到这里，就知道glewInit()返回了一个值
so we know the glewInit() returns a value if we actually look at this
你可以看到这儿
you can see there's
在这个头文件中，没有相关注释
no documentation in the header file
所以，我们需要回到文档页面这里
so we need to go back here
当我们回到文档的Usage页面时
if we go back to our Usage in the documentation
你可以看到glewInit()的返回值
you can see that this return value from glewInit()
如果它当前不是GLEW_OK
if it actually isn't GLEW_OK
那么我们就会看到一个问题
then we have a problem
所以，让我们直接检验那个吧，我想说如果
so let's go ahead and check that I want to say if
glewInit()的返回值不等于GLEW_OK
glewInit() doesn't equal GLEW_OK
也许我们就可以打印点什么
then maybe we can just print something
就像这样，就现在而言
like this, just for now
并且在运行之前，我会在这行设置一个断点
and I'll put a break point on this line before we start
当然，我也不得不去包含iostream这个库
I'll also have to include iostream of course
为了能使用cout
to use cout
所以，按f5，好了，那么我们就在这行代码上
so let's hit f5, okay, so we're on this line of code
按f10
let's hit f10
哦，不，看这个
oh no, look at that
它不等于GLEW_OK
it's not equal to  GLEW_OK
我们得到了一个错误的打印
and we get an error printing
这里发生了什么
what happened
记得我说过是否可以调用glewInit()
well remember when I mentioned whether it was okay to call glewInit()
在glfwInit()之后
after glfwInit()
然后我问你们是不是
and then I asked you guys if it was
然后也许你说了些什么
and then maybe you said something
或者你只是无视我，等着结果
or maybe you just ignored me and waited for the result
那行吧
well
这不对，我们不能在这里调用glewInit()
it's...it's not okay, we can't call glewInit() here
我们不能这样的原因是因为
the reason we can't is because
文档
the documentation
清楚地表明了，你需要创建一个有效的渲染OpenGL上下文
clearly states that you need to create a valid OpenGL rendering context
在我们需要做这个的地方
where do we do this
在glfwMakeContextCurrent()这里，我们创建了OpenGL上下文，对吧
glfwMakeContextCurrent() that is when we create that OpenGL context, okay
所以我们需要做的就是移动这行代码
so what we need to do is move this code
那行代码应该在我们这里一个有效上下文后面
so, that is after we have a valid context
以及一个有效窗口诸如此类的后面
and a valid window and all of that
所以现在，我把它移动到这里来
so now if I move this down here
在这儿设置一个断点，按f5
put a break point here, hit f5
现在当我按下f10
now if I hit f10
看看，它跳过了这里，因为它是对的
look at that it skips over this, because it is okay
并且一切正常
and everything is good
这就是所有的事情
and that's all there is to it
现在，我们就可以访问所有的OpenGL函数了
now we have access to all of the OpenGL functions
我们当然能够用任何版本
that we actually have up to karmas job version
如果我需要使用
and if I want to use
任意一个OpenGL较新版本的OpenGL函数
any of the kind of OpenGL functions that are in newer versions of OpenGL
比如glGenBuffers()，或者诸如此类的
such as glGenBuffers(), or something like that
你可以看到，我能够在这儿输入它
you can see that I can just type it in there
并且它没有问题
and it's fine
如果你看当前的GLEW头文件时
if you look at the actual GLEW header file
所以当我右键点击这里，打开文档
so if I right click here, and go to open document
实际上，这是一个非常大的文件
this is actually a really large file
如果你把它拉到底部
if you just pull down to the bottom
你可以看到它有23,000行代码
you can see it's 23,000 lines of code
它甚至可能会让你的电脑慢一点
it might even slow your computer down a bit
但这个有它的一切和它的运行方式
but this has everything that it is and the way that it works
如果我们粗略地看一下
if we loosely look at it
对于很多函数来说，它的作用是
is that for a lot of functions, what it does is
它实际上定义了函数指针
it actually defines function pointers which are all
这些都是
which is what all of these are
所以如果你要用一个函数
so if you're going to use a function
就像我刚刚写的glGenBuffers()
such as glGenBuffers() like I just did
它实际上，让我们让它简单地工作
it actually and let's just to make this loosely make this kind of work
所以我们需要一个缓冲变量a
so we want one buffer a
实际上，它必须是一个无符号整数
and it actually has to be an unsigned int
不管怎样，这就是我们的函数
but anyway there's our function
如果我们现在看一下函数的定义
if we actually go to that function definition
你可以看到它只是一个哈希定义的宏
you can see it's just a macro as to hash define
所以我们实际要做的是
so what we actually want to do
如果我们想看看函数签名
if we want to look at the function signature
就是通过这个
is go through this
__glewGenBuffers
然后转到这个函数指针的类型
and then go to the type of this function pointer
然后我们看到返回类型是void
and then we get the return type which is avoid
以及取GLsizei类型的参数x
as well as the parameters that takes x GLsizei
一个无符号整数
and an unsigned int
当然
but of course
我们会看到这些，并发现很多
we'll be looking at this and discovering a lot
随着我们OpenGL系列的继续
more of this as our OpenGL journey goes on
这就是你初始化GLEW的方法
that's it that's how you initialize GLEW
这就是你获得现代OpenGL版本的方法
that's how you get to the modern OpenGL version
实际上，我们今天要做的另一件事是
one more thing we'll do for today is actually
打印我们的OpenGL版本只是为了
print our OpenGL version to just
确保我们是最新版本
make sure we're up to date
顺便说一下，这和当前的GLEW没有任何关系
this has nothing to do with actual GLEW by the way
这只是我们应该得到的有用信息
but it's just useful information that we should have
所以我要做的是
so what I'm going to do is
一旦我们有一个有效的OpenGL上下文
once we have a valid OpenGL context
基本上，我就写std::cout
I'm basically just going to write std cout
然后glGetString ()
and then glGetString()
就像这样的GL_VERSION
GL_VERSION just like that
我要移除这个断点
I'm going to remove this break point
按f5，可以看到
hit f5 and you can see that
这里说的是OpenGL4.4
what it says over here is OpenGL 4.4
build blah blah blah
我现在正在用笔记本电脑
I'm actually running on a laptop right now
有Intel的GPU和NVIDIA的
which has an Intel GPU as well as the NVIDIA one
所以这行很明显
so, it's obvious from this line here
它实际上使用Intel显卡来运行这个应用的
it's actually using the Intel GPU for running this application
如果我切换到NVIDIA
if I switch to NVIDIA
应该是NVIDIA的驱动版本
it would have said the NVIDIA driver version
可能是NVIDIA这个单词结尾
and probably the word end NVIDIA
以及更高的OpenGL版本
as well as a higher OpenGL version
但知道实际运行的是什么总是很有用的
but it's always useful to know what you're actually running
所以打印到终端是很有用的操作
so printing that to the console is useful stuff
无论如何，我希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话，可以点击那个喜欢按钮
if you did, you can hit that like button
你也可以帮助
you can also help
支持这个系列并获得一些奖励，比如
support this series and get rewards such as
…
videos early contribute to video planning
your name and the credits all that kind of fun stuff
通过patron
by going to patron comforts actually channel
这真的有助于支持这个系列
it really does help support the series
并且确保
and make sure that
我可以更频繁地为你们更新这些视频
I can make these videos more frequently for you guys
下次再见
I will see you next time goodbye